<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Metropolitan Council</origin><title>Transit Patterns by Node Segments</title><pubinfo><publish>Metropolitan Council</publish></pubinfo><pubdate>20150326</pubdate><onlink>https://gisdata.mn.gov/dataset/us-mn-state-metc-trans-transit-pattern-node-segs</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>The Transit Patterns layer contains all fixed patterns serving the Twin Cities regional metropolitan area. A single route has multiple patterns often characterized by different terminals or branches. One shape and one corresponding record exists for each individual node (time point) segment that compose the pattern. 

Metro Transit defines a node as reference points that make up a route. These are usually street intersections but can be places. Stops are assigned the node id if they are related to the designated intersection or place. At each node location, actual arrival times are recorded and documented in transit systems. Please note that not all stops are assigned a node id. 

The line work for the dataset was derived from NCompasses Street Centerline and Address Range dataset. A small number of line segments have been added to those available from the NCompass dataset to completely depict all patterns traveled by fixed-route transit vehicles. </abstract><purpose>To identify all locations in the Twin Cities metropolitan area where fixed-route transit route patterns exist.</purpose><supplinf>Twin Cities 7 county metropolitan area as well as Sherburne County.  This includes the counties of Anoka, Carver, Dakota, Hennepin, Ramsey, Scott and Washington.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><current>Pattern geography is updated weekly and includes linework from the NCompass street centerline dataset released in late summer or early spring.</current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>Updated Weekly</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Weekly</update></status><crossref><citeinfo><title>- NCompass Street Centerline and Address Range dataset. 
- TransitPatterns, TransitRoutes, TransitStops
</title></citeinfo></crossref><keywords><place><placekey>Twin Cities, Anoka County, Carver County, Dakota County, Hennepin County, Ramsey County, Scott County, Washington County, Sherburne County</placekey></place><theme><themekey>transit, buses, patterns, streets, roads, transportation, node</themekey><themekt>None</themekt></theme></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None</useconst><spdom><bounding><westbc>-94.012</westbc><eastbc>-92.732</eastbc><northbc>45.415</northbc><southbc>44.471</southbc></bounding></spdom><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Sean Murphy</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1371</cntvoice><cntemail>sean.murphy@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>LINE ATTRIBUTES: 

pat_id: A text field identifying the pattern. The first four letters are short-hand for the starting location and the next four letters are short-hand for the ending location.

line_id: A number field identifying the route number associated with the pattern. 

node_id: A text field identifying the unique node. It is often comprised of a four letter abbreviation for two intersecting streets in closest proximity, two letters for each street.

line_direction: Direction the pattern travels. 

term_letter: The terminal letter assigned to the pattern. Patterns with different terminal letters have more than minor variances but not enough to be its own route. These variances may be different end points for the last third of the route or a different way to get to the same end point. 

trip_stop_sequence: The sequence the node occurs. Please note that the sequence is based off of stop order and not every stop is a node. Therefore, the sequence number may jump forward more than one from node to node.</eaover></overview></eainfo><dataqual><complete>The patterns include all versions of a route, which have service information provided on Metro Transit's website.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Positional accuracy varies throughout the dataset. Most line work in most counties falls within the road right of way, often near the center. Recent realignments by the NCompass Street Centerline database have resulted in increased positional accuracy. 

Text below taken from NCompass metadata: 

There are differing degrees of positional accuracy throughout the file. NCompass adjusts the positional accuracy of the data to available sources known to have a greater degrees of accuracy then those used to generate the existing data. However, in all cases (including instances where COGO line work has been the reference) NCompass generalizes the street segments to at least 4 feet in order to greatly reduce the number of vertices - thus reducing unnecessary file size and allowing for faster analysis. 

NCompass goal is to have 95% of roads located to within the approximate center of digital right-of-way data or pavement centerlines provided from counties, where such digital data is available. In other areas, 95% of roads are intended to be within ten meters of the road or right-of-way center.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>This dataset was created in Giro's Hastus scheduling software and referenced the NCompass and Metro Transit street centerline dataset. See the metadata for the NCompass Street Centerline layer for source information.

A summary of other available Transit datasets can be found here:
&lt;a href="TransitDatasets_Commons.pdf" target=_blank&gt;Transit Dataset Summary&lt;/a&gt;</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><distinfo><resdesc>TransitPatternsNodeSegments</resdesc><distliab>NOTICE:  The Geographic Information System (GIS) Data to which this notice is attached are made available pursuant to the Minnesota Government Data Practices Act (Minnesota Statutes Chapter 13).  THE GIS DATA ARE PROVIDED TO YOU AS IS AND WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY AS TO THEIR PERFORMANCE, MERCHANTABILITY, OR FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  The GIS Data were developed by the Metropolitan Council for its own internal business purposes.  The Metropolitan Council does not represent or warrant that the GIS Data or the data documentation are error-free, complete, current, or accurate.  You are responsible for any consequences resulting from your use of the GIS Data or your reliance on the GIS Data.  You should consult the data documentation for this particular GIS Data to determine the limitations of the GIS Data and the precision with which the GIS Data may depict distance, direction, location, or other geographic features.  If you transmit or provide the GIS Data (or any portion of it) to another user, it is recommended that the GIS Data include a copy of this disclaimer and this metadata.</distliab><stdorder><ordering>See Online Linkage Below</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Jon Hoekenga</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS System Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1561</cntvoice><cntemail>jonathan.hoekenga@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20150326</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Metropolitan Council</cntorg><cntper>Sean Murphy</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Specialist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>390 Robert Street North</address><city>St. Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55101-1805</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651.602.1371</cntvoice><cntemail>sean.murphy@metc.state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>